<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<section xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/docbook-ng"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform"
         xml:id="configreference">
  <title>Config options reference</title>
  <section id="options">
    <title>List of core (ie: not for filters) config options:</title>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><option>[global] server.socket_port</option>: port number where the server is listening (defaults to 8080)</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para><option>[global] server.log_file</option>: path to a file to log CherryPy server activity.  Items logged include startup config info, tracebacks and HTTP requests.  It is disabled by default and everything is logged to the screen.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para><option>[global] server.log_access_file</option>: path to a file where access log data will be stored in Common Log Format.  The default is to write access log data to the screen.  If a file is specified, the access log data is no longer written to the screen.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para><option>[global] server.log_to_screen</option>: controls whether any log data is written to the screen.  It defaults to on (True).  For performance reasons, it is best to have this option turned off on a production server.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para><option>[global] server.log_tracebacks</option>: controls whether or not tracebacks are written to the log (screen or otherwise).  Defaults to on (True)  If set to False, only a 500 return code will be logged in the access log.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para><option>[global] server.max_request_header_size</option>: maximum acceptable size of a request header, in bytes (defaults to 500KB). If a longer request arrives, the server will interrupt it and return a 413 error. This setting is global (ie: doesn't depend on the path). Set it to zero to remove the limit</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para><option>[/path] server.max_request_body_size</option>: maximum acceptable size of a request body, in bytes (defaults to 100MB). If a longer request body arrives, the server will interrupt it and return a 413 error. This setting can be configured per path. This is useful to limit the size of uploaded files. Set it to zero to remove the limit</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para><option>TODO</option>: other config options</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
</section>
