<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/docbook-ng"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xml:id="sessions">
  <title>Session Management</title>
  <abstract>
    <para>CherryPy 2.1 includes a powerful sessions system provided via a new
    <literal>sessionFilter</literal>.</para>
  </abstract>
  <section id="usingsessions">
    <title>Using Sessions</title>
    <para>First you need to enable the session filter through the
    configuration system, by setting <option>sessionFilter.on</option> to
    <literal>True</literal>. This gives you a variable called
    <literal>cherrypy.session</literal>, which is a dictionary-like object
    where you can read/store your session data. This dictionary always has a
    special key called <literal>_id</literal> which contains the session
    id.</para>
    <para>Here is sample code showing how to implement a simple counter using
    sessions:</para>
    <example>
            <tile>Basic example of session usage</tile>
      <programlisting>
            import cherrypy
            class Root:
                def index(self):
                    count = cherrypy.session.get('count', 0) + 1
                    cherrypy.session['count'] = count
                    return 'Counter: %s' % count
                index.exposed = True

            cherrypy.config.update({'sessionFilter.on': True})
            cherrypy.root = Root()
            cherrypy.server.start()
            </programlisting>
    </example>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Configuring sessions</title>
    <para>The following configuration options are available for
    "sessionFilter":</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><option>sessionFilter.on</option>: <literal>True</literal> or
        <literal>False</literal> (default): enable/disable sessions</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para><option>sessionFilter.storageType</option>: Specify which
        storage type should be used for storing session data on the server.
        Built-in types are <literal>Ram</literal> (default),
        <literal>File</literal> and <literal>PostgreSQL</literal> (see <xref
        linkend="backends" /> for more info).</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para><option>sessionFilter.storagePath</option>: Specifies the directory 
        in which CherryPy puts the session files when sessionFilter.storageType is set
        to <literal>File</literal>.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para><option>sessionFilter.timeout</option>: The number of minutes of
        inactivity before an individual session can be removed. It can be a
        float (ex: 0.5 for 30 seconds). Defaults to 60.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para><option>sessionFilter.cleanUpDelay</option>: Once in a while the
        server cleans up old/expired sessions. This config option specifies
        how often this clean up process should happen. The delay is in
        minutes. Defaults to 5.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para><option>sessionFilter.cookieName</option>: The name of the
        cookie that CherryPy will use to store the session ID. Defaults to
        <literal>sessionID</literal>.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para><option>sessionFilter.getDB</option>: See the
        <option>PostgreSQL</option> backend from <xref
        linkend="backends" />.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para><option>sessionFilter.deadlockTimeout</option>: See <xref
        linkend="concurrent" />.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para><option>sessionFilter.onCreateSession</option>: See <xref
        linkend="callbacks" />.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para><option>sessionFilter.onDeleteSession</option>: See <xref
        linkend="callbacks" />.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para><option>sessionFilter.storageClass</option>: See <xref
        linkend="custombackend" />.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
  <section id="backends">
    <title>Choosing the backend</title>
    <para>CherryPy comes with multiple build-in backends for storing session
    data on the server side. They are:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><option>Ram</option>: All data is stored in RAM; this is the
        fastest storage, but it means that the data will be lost if you
        restart the server; and it also means that it won't scale to multiple
        processes/machines</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para><option>File</option>: All data is stored on disk; this is a bit
        slower than Ram storage, but the data will persist if you restart the
        server. It also means that data can be shared amongst multiple
        CherryPy processes, either on the same machine, or on multiple
        machines if all machines have access to the same disk (for example,
        via NFS).</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem><para><option>PostgreSQL</option>: This backend is included
      with CherryPy to show how easy it is to implement your own custom
      backend for the session system. All data is stored in a PostgreSQL
      database; storing your data in a database is the recommend setup for
      production if you have a very high traffic website and you need to scale
      your site across multiple machines. To use this backend, you'll need to
      create the following table in your PostgreSQL database: <screen>
                create table session (
                    id varchar(40),
                    data text,
                    expiration_time timestamp
                )
                </screen> </para> You also need to programmatically set the
      <literal>sessionFilter.getDB</literal> config option to a function that
      returns a DB connection.</listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    Note that when using the <literal>Ram</literal> backend, the session data is saved as soon as you stick it in <literal>cherrypy.session</literal>. So even if an error occurs later on in the page handler the data is still saved; this is not the case for the other backends.
  </section>
  <section id="custombackend">
    <title>Writing your own custom backend</title>
    <para>By default, CherryPy comes with 3 built-in backends, but if you have
    specific needs, it is very easy to implement your own custom backend (for
    instance, another database, or an XML-RPC server, ...). To do so, all you
    have to do is write a class that implements the following methods:
    <screen>
            class MyCustomBackend:
                def save(self, id, data, expirationTime):
                    """ Save the session data and expirationTime for that session id """
                def load(self, id):
                    """ Load the session data and expirationTime for 'id' and return
                        a tuple (data, expirationTime) (even if the session is
                        expired). Return None if id doesn't exist. """
                def cleanUp(self):
                    """ Delete expired session data from storage and call
                        'onDeleteSession' for each deleted session id """
            </screen> Note that if you want to use <option>explicit</option>
    locking (see <xref linkend="concurrent" />), you also have to implement
    two extra methods: <literal>acquireLock</literal> and
    <literal>releaseLock</literal>.</para>
    <para>Once you have written this class, you have to programmatically set
    the <literal>sessionFilter.storageClass</literal> config option to this
    class.</para>
    <para>If you need help in writing your own custom backend it is a good
    idea to look at how the current ones (ram, file and postgresql) are
    implemented. They are implemented in the file
    <filename>cherrypy/lib/filter/sessionfilter.py</filename></para>
  </section>
  <section id="concurrent">
    <title>Handling concurrent requests for the same session data</title>
    <para>It is normally quite rare to have two simultaneous requests with the
    same session ID. It means that a same browser is making 2 requests to your
    server at the same time (to dynamic pages ... static data like images
    don't have sessions). However, this case can happen (if you're using
    frames for instance), and it will happen more and more often as more and
    more people start using Ajax.</para>
    <para>In that case, we need to make sure that access to the session data
    is serialized. This way, threads can't both modify the data at the same
    time and leave it in an inconsistent state.</para>
    <para>You can easily make CherryPy serialize access to the session data by setting the <option>sessionFilter.locking</option> config option to <literal>implicit</literal> (the default is <literal>explicit</literal>, which means that CherryPy won't do any locking for you). In the <literal>implicit</literal> mode,
    if a browser makes a second request while a first request is still being
    handled by the server, the second request will block while the first
    request is accessing the data. As soon as the first request is finished
    then the second request will be able to access it.</para>
    <para>This means that the second request will block until the first
    request is finished.</para>
  </section>
  <section id="callbacks">
    <title>Being notified when sessions are created/deleted</title>
    <para>It is possible to configure the <literal>sessionFilter</literal> so
    that it calls some special callback functions from your code when sessions
    are being created/deleted. To do so you have to set the
    <literal>sessionFilter.onCreateSession</literal> and
    <literal>sessionFilter.onDeleteSession</literal> config options. When a
    session is created/deleted, CherryPy will call these functions and pass
    them the session data.</para>
  </section>
</section>
